A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Urban Poverty Program, Director, Office Files of Bernard McDonald FA606
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Urban Poverty Program, Director, Office Files of Bernard McDonald
Bulk, 1979-1989 1974-1989
bulk
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA606
4.4 Cubic Feet
The Urban Poverty (UP) Program was established as a subdivision of the United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) in October 1981, taking over programs formerly administered by the divisions of National Affairs and Education and Public Policy. It administered programs benefiting the poor and inner-city residents in areas that included community development, employment and training, welfare, teen pregnancy, poverty, crime, and precollege education. In 1988, UP became a program area within a newly organized Program Division and in 1996, was merged into the Asset Building and Community Development Program (ASSETS). Bernard McDonald joined the Ford Foundation National Affairs Division in 1978 as a Program Officer in Social Development. He then served as Program Officer In Charge/Director of Urban Poverty from 1981 to1987. In 1987, he became Director of the Special Project in Community Development in the USIAP Office of the Vice President. His work in Urban Poverty focused on supporting the efforts of poor communities to build their own economic enterprises and building the economic capacities of minority individuals through education and job training. His files span in date from 1974 to 1989 and consist of correspondence, memoranda, proposals, reports, grantee and proposal evaluations, meeting materials, and background information documenting his work in Urban Poverty. The bulk of files concern the management of grants and Program Related Investments to community development corporations (CDCs). There are also files on the Minority Pipeline Task Force, the Rural America Task Force, and the Refugee and Migrants Task Force as well as on the subject of Human Rights and Governance and the Foundation’s Physical, Economic and Social Revitalization strategy area.
(11 Hollinger document boxes)
Biographical/Historical note
The work of what became the Urban Poverty Program began when the Public Affairs Program was formally established in 1952. One of the goals of the new program was to work toward greater equality of opportunity for minority groups. In 1965, Public Affairs was succeeded by the National Affairs Division, created to focus on deep-rooted problems facing American society. Program areas under the National Affairs Division included Social Development and Urban and Metropolitan Development. In 1981, a reorganization of the Foundation replaced National Affairs with the United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP).
The Urban Poverty Program was established in October 1981 as a subdivision of USIAP, taking over programs formerly administered by the divisions of National Affairs and Education and Public Policy. It administered programs benefiting the poor and inner-city residents in areas that included community development, employment and training, welfare, teen pregnancy, poverty, crime, and precollege education. It also assumed oversight of the programs in Population and of new programs to combat infant and child mortality. The Urban Poverty Program became a program area within a newly organized Program Division in 1988 and was merged into the Asset Building and Community Development Program (ASSETS) in 1996.
Biographical/Historical note
Bernard McDonald graduated from Hunter College in 1964 with a B.A. in Economics and received an M.A. in Secondary Education from Brooklyn College in 1968. In 1979, he joined the Ford Foundation National Affairs Division as a Program Officer in Social Development. He then served as Program Officer In Charge/Director of Urban Poverty from 1981 to1987. In 1987, he became Director of the Special Project in Community Development in the United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) Office of the Vice President. His work in Urban Poverty focused on supporting the efforts of poor communities to build their own economic enterprises and building the economic capacities of minority individuals through education and job training. To this end, sustaining and building the capacity of community development corporations (CDCs) committed to physical, economic, and social revitalization became a vital component of the Foundation’s strategic approach to alleviating urban poverty. This was carried out through making long-term grants and Program Related Investments (PRIs) to numerous CDCs.
Mr. McDonald also served on the Ford Foundation Minority Pipeline, Rural America, and Refugee and Migrant task forces. The Minority Pipeline Task Force, later renamed the Committee to Improve the Professional Opportunities for Minorities, aimed to increase minority access to professional fields through implementing progressive affirmative action policies in the Foundation’s grantmaking. Through the Task Force, the Foundation funded scholarships, internships and research opportunities for minority students and scholars. The Rural America Task Force was funded by a Delegated Authority Project (DAP) grant and was charged with improving agricultural productivity, irrigation, and opportunities for rural employment. The Refugee and Migrants Task Force focused on aiding refugees resettling in the United States, particularly from Haiti and Southeast Asia.
Mr. McDonald left the Foundation in October 1989 for a faculty position at the Pratt Institute. There, he directed the Ford Foundation-sponsored Community Development Corporation Oral History Project. He died in 1991 at age 49.
Scope and Contents note
The Office Files of Bernard McDonald span in date from 1974 to 1989 and primarily document his work in Urban Poverty. The collection consists of chron files, files on Program Related Investments, and files relating to his administering of grants and service on various task forces.
Many of the Grant-Related and Program Related Investment files pertain to the Foundation’s support of community development corporations (CDCs), particularly the South East Alabama Self-Help Association (SEASHA), Mississippi Action for Community Education (MACE) and organizations in the South Bronx. Delegated Authority Project (DAP) grants and Program Related Investments (PRIs) constitute the bulk of the grant activity documented in the files.
Program and Grant-Related Files also include files on the Minority Pipeline Task Force (1985-1987), the Rural America Task Force (1980-1985), and the Refugee and Migrants Task Force (1982-1983). The files on the Minority Pipeline Task Force contain memoranda and meeting summaries discussing efforts to increase minority representation in professional fields. Also within these files is Mr. Bernard’s working file on implementing the Foundation’s internal affirmative action policies (1983-1985). The Rural America Task Force files (1980-1985) contain Delegated-Authority Project (DAP) grant proposals, proposal evaluations, progress reports, meeting minutes, seminar action programs, and related background information.
Separated Materials note
Appendix A: Reports – Unpublished reports written by Ford Foundation staff and consultants were removed from their original folders, scanned and transferred to the Archives' collection of staff and consultant reports. See Appendix A for a list of these reports and their specific assigned number. The reports are listed in alphabetical order by author. The assigned number may be used to access reports in the online catalog.
Conditions Governing Access note
Material more than ten years old is open for scholarly research.
Select individual files are restricted, as noted. Permission to access these files must be obtained from the Ford Foundation before scholarly access is permitted.
Arrangement
Arranged into 3 series.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be restricted from scholarly research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment. Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be restricted from scholarly research at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/RAC Head of Reference.
Ford Foundation
- Correspondence, 1979-1989; I
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains Mr. McDonald’s chronological correspondence files dating from 1979 to 1989. The files include reports on site visits and memoranda concerning then-ongoing grant activity and programs.
  - 1979 Chronological Files -- General (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1980 Chronological Files -- General (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1982 Chronological Files -- General (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1983 Chronological Files -- General (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1984 Chronological Files -- General (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1985 Chronological Files -- General (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1986 Chronological Files -- General (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1987 Chronological Files -- General -- A-M (1 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1987 Chronological Files -- General -- Mc-Z (2 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1988 Chronological Files -- General -- A-M (1 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1988 Chronological Files -- General -- Mc-Z (2 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1989 Chronological Files -- General -- A-M (1 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 1989 Chronological Files -- General -- Mc-Z (2 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Program and Grant-Related Files, 1974-1989; II
  The files in this series hold correspondence, memoranda, evaluations, meeting notes, agenda and background material pertaining to proposed or then-ongoing grant activity, ongoing Foundation programs, and collaboration with other philanthropies and organizations. Also included are files on the Minority Pipeline Task Force, the Rural America Task Force, and the Refugee and Migrants Task Force as well as on CDCs such as the South East Alabama Self-Help Association (SEASHA), Mississippi Action for Community Education (MACE), and the South Bronx Development Organization (SBDO).
  There are also files dating between 1979 and 1986 about the Manpower Demonstration Research Corporation, a non-profit organization in labor research created in 1974 by a consortium of federal agencies and the Ford Foundation. A few files relate to the Neighborhood Security and Crime Prevention Program (1980-1987), a continuation of the Foundation’s ongoing work in community revitalization and redevelopment. Also within this series are Mr. Bernard’s correspondence on the subject of Human Rights and Governance (1983-1987) and files on the Foundation’s Physical, Economic and Social Revitalization strategy area (1980-1987).
  Arrangement
  Arranged aphabetically by folder title.
  - Affirmative Action -- Memoranda, Report Re: Ford Foundation Affirmative Action Policies, 1983-1985 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Asa T. Spaulding Autobiography -- Correspondence, Background on Spaulding, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Comprehensive Competencies Program (CCP) Learning Centers -- Memoranda Re: Site Visit, Mar 3, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Consultants -- Anderson, Bernard -- Re: Evaluation of Ford Foundation East African Urban Poverty Program, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Consultants -- Callender, Dr. Eugene S. -- Re: Withdrawn Consultancy on Youthful Ex-Offenders, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Consultants -- Digilio, James -- Correspondence Re: Consultancy on Technical Assistance, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Consultants -- Dunn, Marvin -- Memoranda Re: Book on Miami Riots, 1981-1983 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Consultants -- Grinker, Walker Associates Inc. -- Correspondence Re: Evaluation of Urban Educational Systems, Urban Institutes, Police Foundation, 1983-1986 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Consultants -- Krauskopf, Jack -- Re: Ford Foundation Homeless Strategy, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Consultants -- Logue, Ken -- Re: Block Grant Evaluation Report, Community Partnership, 1981-1988 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Consultants -- Rowser, Sharon -- Correspondence Re: Consultancy to Complete Assignments, Jun 19 - Nov 14, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Consultants -- Urban Partners -- John Gallery -- Evaluation of Enterprise Foundation, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Education -- Child Education -- Organized by Shelby H. Miller -- Memoranda Re: Children's Defense Fund and Women's Education, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Education -- City High School Recognition Program -- Organized by Edward J. Meade Jr. -- Teacher Development Memoranda and Program Background, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Education -- Early Childhood Education/Child Care Group -- Briefing Papers, Meeting Agenda, Meeting Materials, 1984-1986 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Education (General) -- Memoranda from Edward J. Meade, Jr., 1981-1983 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Education (General) -- Organized by Barbara S. Nelson -- Memoranda Re: Ford Foundation Education Program and Grants, 1984-1987 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Education -- Public Secondary Schools -- Organized by Edward J. Meade, Jr. -- Memoranda Re: Ford Foundation Grants to Schools, 1984-1987 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Ellis Island Foundation -- Memoranda and Background on Centennial Rehabilitation Funding, Jun 3 - Dec 15, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Ford Foundation Press Releases, 1982-1985 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - "Ford, Logue, and the Bronx" (report) by Bruce Porter, Nov 21, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Funders' Committee for Voter Registration and Education -- Summary Discussion, Oct 29, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - "Highlights of the Ford Foundation-Supported Activities in the City of Pittsburgh", Nov 1984 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Human Rights and Governance, 1983-1987 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - "Innovations in State and Local Government", 1986 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Immigration -- Haitian Task Force -- Progress Reports, Board Meeting Minutes, Background, 1984-1986 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Immigration -- Organized by Patricia Biggers -- Memoranda Re: Haitian Centers, Refugee Group, Film on Immigration in America, etc. (1 of 2), 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Immigration -- Organized by Patricia Biggers -- Memoranda Re: Ford Foundation Immigration Grantmaking (2 of 2), 1984-1987 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Manpower Demonstration Research Corporation -- Bimonthly Reports, Notes, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Manpower Demonstration Research Corporation -- Project Redirection -- Correspondence, Memoranda, Meeting Agenda, Fact Sheet, Clippings, 1979-1986 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Manpower Demonstration Research Corporation -- Project Redirection -- Executive Summary Reports, Status and Planning Report, 1981-1982 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Manpower Demonstration Research Corporation -- Project Redirection -- Quarterly Reports, 1983-1985 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Minority Pipeline Task Force -- Committee to Improve the Professional Opportunities for Minorities -- Funding Requests, Memoranda Re: Increasing Minority Participation (1 of 3), Jan - Aug 1985 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Minority Pipeline Task Force -- Committee to Improve the Professional Opportunities for Minorities -- Funding Requests, Status Reports, Minority Rights Program Review (2 of 3), Sep - Dec 1985 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Minority Pipeline Task Force -- Committee to Improve the Professional Opportunities for Minorities -- Memoranda Re: Funding Requests, Meeting Summaries (3 of 3), 1986-1987 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Mott Foundation Visit to Discuss PRI -- Schedule, Program Officer's Guide, Issue Paper, May 17-Sep 20, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Neighborhood Security and Crime Prevention -- Correspondence, Proposal and Memoranda Re: Eisenhower Foundation, South Forty, etc., 1980-1982 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Neighborhood Security and Crime Prevention -- Organized by Sharon L. Rowser -- Memoranda Re: Proposed Grants, Address on Policing, etc., 1982-1984 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Neighborhood Security and Crime Prevention -- Memoranda and Notes on Police Foundation Evaluation, Arson Strike Force Report, Update on Initiative, Background, Nov 22, 1982-Jul 27, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Neighborhood Security and Crime Prevention -- Organized by Craig Howard -- Memoranda on People's Firehouse, Racial Violence, etc., Nov 13, 1986-Apr 17, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Office of the President -- Correspondence Re: Fugazy Express Proposal with Background, 1983-1988 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Physical, Economic, and Social Revitalization Program -- Community Development Corporations (CDCs) -- Memoranda from Ghebre Mehreteab, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Physical, Economic, and Social Revitalization Program -- Community Economic Development Training Workshops Organized by Ghebre Mehreteab, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Physical, Economic, and Social Revitalization -- Interface Interim Project Report, Memoranda Re: CDCs, Correspondence Re: Ford Foundation PRIs, Nov 13, 1980-Dec 11, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Physical, Economic, and Social Revitalization -- Memoranda Re: Indochinese Economic Development Center, Minority Business Information Institute, Women and Foundations, etc., Jan 25-Nov 12, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Physical, Economic, and Social Revitalization -- Correspondence Re: Ongoing Ford Foundation-Supported PRIs, Site Visit, Update, Mar 24-Dec 17, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Physical, Economic, and Social Revitalization -- Status Report and Meetings, Memoranda Re: CDCs and Address to Regional Association of Grantmakers, May 6-Jun 11, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Physical, Economic, and Social Revitalization -- Proposals, Memoranda Re: Criteria for Selecting Emerging Urban CDCs, Apr 15-Jun 29, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Physical, Economic, and Social Revitalization -- Grant Proposals, Grant Updates, Child Care Conference Information (1 of 2), 1983-1984 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Physical, Economic, and Social Revitalization -- Summary of Urban Poverty Physical Economic and Social Revitalization (PES) Grants, Grant Proposals, Project Updates (2 of 2), 1985-1987 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Pittsburgh Foundation Annual Retreat -- Agenda, Notes, Program, Jun 16-18, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Pittsburgh Partnership for Neighborhood Development -- Assessment Reports, News Clippings, Remarks, Press Releases, Background, 1983-1985 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Police Foundation -- Memoranda, Evaluation, Newspaper Article, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Population -- Fair Start and Child Survival -- Organized by Oscar Harkavy -- Resource Center Concept Paper, Site Visit Reports, Memoranda on Liability Insurance, etc., 1983-1986 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Population -- Fair Start and Child Survival -- Organized by Oscar Harkavy -- Overview of Initiative, Memoranda Re: Final Technical Reports, Data Collection, Grants, etc., 1986-1987 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Population -- Fair Start and Child Survival -- Organized by Marsha Hunter -- Memoranda Re: Site Visits, Obstetrics Program, Possible MCH Outreach Conference, Grant Proposal Comments, etc., Mar 27, 1984-Sep 24, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Population -- Fair Start and Child Survival -- Memoranda, Agenda for Program Meeting in Kathmandu, Nepal, Mar-Apr 1986 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Poverty Research -- Memoranda Re: Ford Foundation Involvement with Economic Research, Minorities, and Proposed Grants, Oct 7 - Dec 15, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Public Policy and Social Organization (PPSO) -- Basil J. Whiting Resignation, Information on the Aging/Elderly, 1975-1977 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Public Policy and Social Organization (PPSO) -- Memoranda Re: Proposal Evaluations and Recommendations for DAP Grant Action, Meeting Minutes, Correspondence, Proposals (1 of 4), Jul-Sep 1980 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Public Policy and Social Organization (PPSO) -- Memoranda Re: Proposal Evaluations and Recommendations for DAP Grant Action, Meeting Minutes, Correspondence, Proposals (2 of 4), Oct-Dec 1980 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Public Policy and Social Organization (PPSO) -- Memoranda Re: Proposal Evaluations and Recommendations for DAP Grant Action, Meeting Minutes, Correspondence, Proposals (3 of 4), Jan-Mar 1981 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Public Policy and Social Organization (PPSO) -- Memoranda Re: Proposal Evaluations and Recommendations for DAP Grant Action, Meeting Minutes, Correspondence, Proposals (4 of 4), Mar-Sep 1981 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Public Secondary Schools -- Institute for Educational Leadership -- Report, News Clippings, 1981-1983 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Refugees and Migrants -- Correspondence and Memoranda Re: Indochina Refugee Action Center, South East Asia Refugees (1 of 2), 1982 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Refugees and Migrants -- U.S.-Mexico Trip, Memoranda Re: Haitian Centers, Caravajal Foundation, Ford Foundation Refugees and Migrant Group (2 of 2), 1983 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Reproductive Health Group -- Memoranda, Correspondence, 1983-1985 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Rural America Task Force -- DAP Grant Proposal for Funding to Improve Public Policy for Rural Areas of the United States, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Rural America Task Force -- Meeting and Staff Seminar on Community Level Action Programs, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Rural America Task Force -- Memoranda Re: Meetings and Progress Report, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Rural America Task Force -- Memoranda Re: Proposal Evaluations and Recommendations for DAP Grant Action, Meeting Minutes, Correspondence, Proposals, Report (1 of 4), Jan-Jun 1980 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Rural America Task Force -- Memoranda Re: Proposal Evaluations and Recommendations for DAP Grant Action, Meeting Minutes, Correspondence, Proposals (2 of 4), Jun-Sep 1980 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Rural America Task Force -- Memoranda Re: Proposal Evaluations and Recommendations for DAP Grant Action, Meeting Minutes, Correspondence, Proposals (3 of 4), Aug 1980-Mar 1981 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Rural America Task Force -- Memoranda Re: Proposal Evaluations and Recommendations for DAP Grant Action, Meeting Minutes, Correspondence, Proposals (4 of 4), Feb-Jul 1981 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Rural America Task Force -- National Rural Center -- Correspondence, Memoranda, Notes, Background, Proposal, 1980-1981 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - South East Alabama Self-Help Association (SEASHA) DAP Grant -- DAP, Site Visit Report, Background and Related Correspondence, 1974-1979 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - South Bronx Development Organization, Inc. (SBDO) -- Correspondence, Report Session Agenda, Report, 1979-1983 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - South Bronx Development Organization, Inc. (SBDO) -- Memoranda Re: Proposal Evaluations and Recommended DAP Grant Action, Proposals, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Special Project on Budget Development -- Reports, Memoranda Re: Special Project and Outside Interests, 1987-1989 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Task Force on the Economy -- Meeting Summary, Agenda, Next Steps, Preliminary Findings and Recommendations, 1985-1987 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Task Force on Work and Family -- Memoranda, Papers, Notes, May 13, 1987 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Trip Reports -- Notes from Trips Overseas, 1987 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Urban Education Program -- Reports, Clippings, Correspondence, Memoranda, 1979-1985 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Welfare and Teenage Pregnancy -- Memoranda Re: Welfare Requests, Proposals, Grant and Program Reports, DAPs, 1984-1987 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Women's Program Forum -- Memoranda, Papers, Symposium Agenda, 1986-1987 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Youth Employment and Training -- Memoranda Re: Proposed Grant Reviews, Grameen Bank and Bangladesh (1 of 2), 1982-1985 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Youth Employment and Training -- Memoranda Re: Reviews of Proposed Grants, Meeting on Industrial Competitiveness (2 of 2), 1985-1987 (Box 9, Folder 9)